Guide to the Ronald Bracewell Papers SC0896
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ronald Bracewell papers
1958-2007
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bracewell, Ronald N. (Ronald Newbold)
SC0896
71.25 Linear Feet
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical / Historical
Ronald Newbold Bracewell (July 22, 1921 – August 12, 2007) was the Lewis M. Terman Professor of Electrical Engineering, Emeritus of the Space, Telecommunications and Radioscience Laboratory at Stanford University.
He was born in Sydney, Australia, in 1921, and educated at Sydney Boys High School. He graduated from the University of Sydney in 1941 with the B.Sc. degree in mathematics and physics, later receiving the degrees of B.E. (1943), and M.E. (1948) with first class honours, and while working in the Engineering Department became the President of the Oxometrical Society. During World War II he designed and developed microwave radar equipment in the Radiophysics Laboratory of the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation, Sydney under the direction of Joseph L. Pawsey and Edward G. Bowen and from 1946 to 1949 was a research student at Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, engaged in ionospheric research in the Cavendish Laboratory, where he received his Ph.D. degree in physics under J. A. Ratcliffe.
From October 1949 to September 1954 Dr. Bracewell was a Senior Research Officer at the Radiophysics Laboratory of the CSIRO, Sydney, concerned with very long wave propagation and radio astronomy. He then lectured in radio astronomy at the Astronomy Department of the University of California, Berkeley from September 1954 to June 1955 at the invitation of Otto Struve, and at Stanford University during the summer of 1955, and joined the Electrical Engineering faculty at Stanford in December 1955. In 1974 he was appointed the first Lewis M. Terman Professor and Fellow in Electrical Engineering (1974–1979). Though he retired in 1979, he continued to be active until his death.
Professor Bracewell was a Fellow of the Royal Astronomical Society (1950), Fellow and life member of the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers (1961), Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1989), and was a Fellow with other significant societies and organisations.
For experimental contributions to the study of the ionosphere by means of very low frequency waves, Dr. Bracewell received the Duddell Premium of the Institution of Electrical Engineers, London in 1952. In 1992 he was elected to foreign associate membership of the Institute of Medicine of the U.S. National Academy of Sciences (1992), the first Australian to achieve that distinction, for fundamental contributions to medical imaging. He was one of Sydney University's three honourees when alumni awards were instituted in 1992, with a citation for brain scanning, and was the 1994 recipient of the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers' Heinrich Hertz medal for pioneering work in antenna aperture synthesis and image reconstruction as applied to radio astronomy and to computer-assisted tomography. In 1998 Dr. Bracewell was named Officer of the Order of Australia (AO) for service to science in the fields of radio astronomy and image reconstruction. At CSIRO Radiophysics Laboratory, work that in 1942-1945 was classified appeared in a dozen reports. Activities included design, construction, and demonstration of voice-modulation equipment for a 10 cm magnetron (July 1943), a microwave triode oscillator at 25 cm using cylindrical cavity resonators, equipment designed for microwave radar in field use (wavemeter, echo box, thermistor power meter, etc.) and microwave measurement technique. Experience with numerical computation of fields in cavities led, after the war, to a Master of Engineering degree (1948) and the definitive publication on step discontinuities in radial transmission lines (1954).
While at the Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge (1946–1950) Bracewell worked on observation and theory of upper atmospheric ionisation, contributing to experimental technique (1948), explaining solar effects (1949), and distinguishing two layers below the E-layer (1952), work recognised by the Duddell Premium.
At Stanford Professor Bracewell constructed a microwave spectroheliograph (1961), a large and complex radio telescope which produced daily temperature maps of the sun reliably for eleven years, the duration of a solar cycle. The first radio telescope to give output automatically in printed form, and therefore capable of worldwide dissemination by teleprinter, its daily solar weather maps received acknowledgement from NASA for support of the first manned landing on the moon. Many fundamental papers on restoration (1954–1962), interferometry (1958–1974) and reconstruction (1956–1961) appeared along with instrumental and observational papers. By 1961 the radio-interferometer calibration techniques developed for the spectroheliograph first allowed an antenna system, with 52" fan beam, to equal the angular resolution of the human eye in one observation. With this beam the components of Cygnus A, spaced 100", were put directly in evidence without the need for repeated observations with variable spacing aperture synthesis interferometry.
The nucleus of the extragalactic source Centaurus A was resolved into two separate components whose right ascensions were accurately determined with a 2.3-minute fan beam at 9.1 cm. Knowing that Centaurus A was composite, Bracewell used the 6.7-minute beam of the Parkes Observatory 64 m radiotelescope at 10 cm to determine the separate declinations of the components and in so doing was the first to observe strong polarisation in an extragalactic source (1962), a discovery of fundamental significance for the structure and role of astrophysical magnetic fields. Subsequent observations made at Parkes by other observers with a 14-minute and wider beams at 21 cm and longer wavelengths, though not resolving the components, were compatible with the λ2 dependence expected from Faraday rotation if magnetic fields were the polarising agent.
A second major radiotelescope (1971) employing advanced concepts to achieve an angular resolution of 18 seconds of arc was designed and built at Stanford and applied to both solar and galactic studies. The calibration techniques for this leading-edge resolution passed into general use in radio interferometry via the medium of alumni.
Upon the discovery of the cosmic background radiation: a remarkable observational limit of 1.7 millikelvins, with considerable theoretical significance for cosmology, was set on the anisotropy in collaboration with Ph. D. student E.K. Conklin (1967), and was not improved on for many years; the correct theory of a relativistic observer in a blackbody enclosure (1968) was given in the first of several papers by various authors obtaining the same result; the absolute motion of the Sun at 308 km/s through the cosmic background radiation was measured by Conklin in 1969, some years before independent confirmation.
With the advent of the space age, Bracewell became interested in celestial mechanics, made observations of the radio emission from Sputnik 1, and supplied the press with accurate charts predicting the path of Soviet satellites, which were perfectly visible, if you knew when and where to look. Following the puzzling performance of Explorer I in orbit, he published the first explanation (1958-9) of the observed spin instability of satellites, in terms of the Poinsot motion of a non-rigid body with internal friction. He recorded the signals from Sputniks I, II and III and discussed them in terms of the satellite spin, antenna polarisation, and propagation effects of the ionised medium, especially Faraday effect.
Later (1978, 1979) he invented a spinning, nulling, two-element infrared interferometer suitable for space-shuttle launching into an orbit near Jupiter, with milliarcsecond resolution, that could lead to the discovery of planets around stars other than the sun. This concept was elaborated in 1995 by Angel and Woolf, whose space-station version with four-element double nulling became the Terrestrial Planet Finder (TPF), NASA's candidate for imaging planetary configurations of other stars (Scientific American, April 1996).
Imaging in astronomy led to participation in development of computer assisted x-ray tomography, where commercial scanners reconstruct tomographic images using the algorithm developed by Bracewell for radioastronomical reconstruction from fan-beam scans. This corpus of work has been recognized by the Institute of Medicine, an award by the University of Sydney, and the Heinrich Hertz medal. Service on the founding editorial board of the Journal for Computer-Assisted Tomography, to which he also contributed publications, and on the scientific advisory boards of medical instrumentation companies maintained Bracewell's interest in medical imaging, which became an important part of his regular graduate lectures on imaging, and forms an important part of his 1995 text on imaging.
Experience with the optics, mechanics and control of radiotelescopes led to involvement with solar thermophotovoltaic energy at the time of the energy crisis, including the fabrication of low-cost solid and perforated paraboloidal reflectors by hydraulic inflation.
Bracewell is also known for being the first to propose the use of autonomous interstellar space probes for of communication between alien civilisations as an alternative to radio transmission dialogs. This hypothetical concept has been dubbed the Bracewell probe after its inventor.
As a consequence of relating images to Fourier analysis, in 1983 he discovered a new factorisation of the discrete Fourier transform matrix leading to a fast algorithm for spectral analysis. This method, which has advantages over the fast Fourier algorithm, especially for images, is treated in The Hartley Transform (1986), in U.S. Patent 4,646,256 (1987, now in the public domain), and in over 200 technical papers by various authors that were stimulated by the discovery. Analogue methods of creating a Hartley transform plane first with light and later with microwaves were demonstrated in the laboratory and permitted the determination of electromagnetic phase by the use of square-law detectors. A new elementary signal representation, the Chirplet transform, was discovered (1991) that complements the Gabor elementary signal representations used in dynamic spectral analysis (with the property of meeting the bandwidth-duration minimum associated with the uncertainty principle). This advance opened a new field of adaptive dynamic spectra with wide application in information analysis.
Professor Bracewell was interested in conveying an appreciation of the role of science in society to the public, in mitigating the effects of scientific illiteracy on public decision making through contact with alumni groups, and in liberal undergraduate education within the framework of the Astronomy Course Program and the Western Culture program in Values, Technology, Science and Society, in both of which he taught for some years. He gave the 1996 Bunyan Lecture on The Destiny of Man.
Among colleagues at Stanford, Bracewell also was known for his insatiable appetite for knowledge in general, whether it was regarding local flora or foreign languages. The Stanford Alumni Association often called on Bracewell to lecture on topics related to space, Renaissance technology and scientific illiteracy; through the alumni association, Bracewell published a book titled The Galactic Club: Intelligent Life in Outer Space.
In 2005, the Stanford Historical Society debuted a 300-page book by Bracewell that catalogs the more than 350 species of trees on campus, titled Trees of Stanford and Environs. Over the years, Bracewell led many tree tours around campus and, in the late 1970s, taught an undergraduate seminar titled I Dig Trees.
Bracewell was also a designer and builder of sundials. He built one on the South side of the Terman Engineering Building. He built one at the home of his son, Mark Bracewell. He built another on the deck of professor John Linvill's house. As his seminar "I Dig Trees" indicated, Dr. Bracewell was known for having a tremendously keen, intelligent sense of wry, science-infused humor. One of his treasured family photos showed him sitting on the ground, legs akimbo, with a beer bottle in front of him that he had neatly balanced on one of its bottom edges—his proof that even that thin edge had 3 balance points.
Professor Bracewell was survived by his wife, a son, Mark, a daughter, Wendy, and two grandchildren.
Related Materials
The Archives at The National Radio Astronomy Observatory is the repository for Ronald N. Bracewell's papers on radio astronomy: http://www.nrao.edu/archives/Bracewell/bracewell.shtml
Bracewell, Ronald N. (Ronald Newbold)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2000-031
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 1)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2008-135
  - Assorted bundles from "desk top" (Box 1)
  - EE262 notes (Box 2)
  - EE446 syllabus and exams (Box 2)
  - Notebook: EE249 STAR (Box 2)
  - Pam box: EE262 materials (Box 2)
  - Bundle: EE249 STAR (Box 2)
  - Tau Beta material (course review) (Box 3)
  - Solar reprints, technical reports, proposals (mostly not by RNB) (Box 3)
  - Print outs of sun map data (Box 3)
  - SU Computation Center "Subalgol Reference Manual" October 1965 (Box 3)
  - Sun photos and data (Box 3)
  - Binder: "Solar 60 day avge (?) maps 1965" (Box 4)
  - Binders: information on solar energy 1974-77 (Box 4)
  - Files on solar concentrator (Box 4)
  - Binder: Photovoltaic Solar Energy System, CBC Laboratories (Box 4)
  - Binder: Solar TPV Glints, by RNB (Box 4)
  - Lab notebook of RNB, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Assorted publications on solar (Box 5)
  - Assorted publications on sea ice (Box 5)
  - ENG25, Astronomy lectures 1975-79 (Box 5)
  - More astronomy lectures, exams (Box 5)
  - Binder: OUP programs (Box 5)
  - Binder: D. S. Evans programs 1984 (Box 6)
  - Astronomy (ENG25) exams (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 6)
  - Binder: "The Hartley Transform" by RNB 1986 (Box 6)
  - The Nucleus (Univ. of Sydney publication) 1970s (Box 6)
  - Sydney Sussex College Annual 1970s (Box 6)
  - Notebook: Committee on Investment Responsibility [CIR] 1977 (Box 7)
  - Folder: Pierre Noyes – articles, some correspondence (Box 7)
  - CIR manual (Box 7)
  - CIR clippings 1977 (Box 7)
  - 2 bundles to be sorted: "Corner Window" – clippings, articles, etc. (Box 7)
  - Solar power reprints (Box 8)
  - EPRI Proposal data (Box 8)
  - Files, publications on "Concentrator" (Box 8)
  - Pubs for possible discard: Annual Review of Energy and 1 v. from Encyclopedia of Art (Box 8)
  - Glass tube [small box inside ½ mb] (Box 9)
  - Lab notebooks: (Box 10)
    - U-222, RNB, Sperial trig & cross surveying, 1955-60 (Box 10)
    - U-310, S. Harris, 23 Oct. 1956 (Box 10)
    - U-302, Yang, 3 Oct. 1956 (Box 10)
    - U-308, RNB, 7-19-56 "Equipment book" (Box 10)
  - Reprints of R. H. T. Bates, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Microwave product information (Box 10)
  - Pensée; Student Academic Freedom Forum; "Immanuel Velikovsky Reconsidered" 10 issues 1972-74 (Box 10)
  - Folder: clippings, 3 books and other items on Immanuel Velikovsky (Box 10)
  - Small box: Bill Parker Archives (S.U. Arborist) – planting maps (some may be copies), articles (Box 10)
  - Corrected proofs for "The Fourier Transform and Its Applications" 1966 (Box 11)
  - Books and pamphlets on scientific writing and guidelines issued by specific journals or publishers (Box 11)
  - Folder of miscellaneous notes (Box 11)
  - 2 Russian Atlases (world – but in small format) (Box 11)
  - Tree correspondence 1972-2003 and assorted other materials on trees (Box 12)
  - Notebook from/for his tree walks (Box 13)
  - Correspondence (Box 13)
  - Leaf prints (mostly in printed form) (Box 13)
  - Files on trees (Box 13)
  - Old aerial photos of Stanford land (Box 14)
  - Leaf prints, mostly photocopied (Box 14)
  - Assorted files on trees (articles, correspondence, maps, a few photos, etc.) (Box 14)
  - 3 notebooks of tree research (Box 15)
  - 2 notebooks of his publication "Trees of Stanford and Environs (Box 15)
  - Dried leaves and other tree parts (Box 16)
- Additional papers, Accession ARCH-2008-291
  - Personnel files [contains some confidential/restricted materials] (Box 1)
  - Files from work with Committee of Fifteen (Box 1)
  - Binder: Program in Structured Liberal Education, Syllabus Winter 1982 (Box 2)
  - Binder: Western Culture 1980 (Box 2)
  - Binder: VTS 2, Winter 1982 (Box 2)
  - Binder: Western Culture – Galileo [sources] 1980 (Box 2)
  - Binder: EE278 Autumn 1989 (Box 2)
  - Binder: VTS 2, January 1981 (Box 2)
  - Several folders on Western Culture Program Committee 1985-86 (Box 2)
  - 1 folder on nominees for Boothe Essay prize for work done in Autumn 1985 (Box 2)
  - EE262 Agenda (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - EE262 and miscellaneous items (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Problem 9.21 of Fourier Transform and Its Applications, correspondence and notes 1977-78 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Assorted articles, possibly for EE262 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1970 and materials re student unrest (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Tau Beta Pi – student course evaluations 1988-89; 1990-91 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Science Responsibility [formerly in a notebook] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Western Culture – VTS 2 – Projects, 1980-82 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "A Proposal for a Program in Values, Technology and Society; Toward Modern General Education for Undergraduates, Stanford University," February 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - VTS 1 assorted materials (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Western Culture 1978-80 [formerly in a notebook] (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Course related materials (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Agenda 98 [mostly printed emails of 1997] (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Bush order [re post 9/11 tribunals] (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Decision Advisory Board, Stanford University in the Matter of Professor H. Bruce Franklin, January 5, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - EE249 final exam Autumn 1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Western Culture Decisions January 1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - EE Dept. Plans 1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - STAR lab 1990 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Citation EE 1988 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Miscellany (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - SRAI reprints (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Bundle of technical reports from Stanford Electronics Laboratory by Bracewell and others (Box 3)
  - Folders on Ph.D. qualifying exams (Box 4)
  - Bd. Item: D. Wells, Guide to GPS Positioning (Box 4)
  - Bd. Item; Clark E. Cohen, Attitude Determination Using GPS, Ph.D. thesis 1992 (Box 4)
  - Loose materials pertaining to courses 1989-1997 (Box 4)
  - Notebook: EE252 1989 Handouts Antennas (Box 4)
- Additional papers: EE 262 lectures, Accession ARCH-2010-078
  - EE 262 lecture, January 11, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, January 13, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, January 18, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, January 20, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, January 23, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, January 25, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, January 27, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, January 30, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 1, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 3, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 6, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 8, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 13, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 15, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 17, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 22, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 24, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, February 37, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 1, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 3, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 6, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 8, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 10, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 13, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 15, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 262 lecture, March 17, 1989; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - Radiowave Scattering from Discrete Surface Structure, J. Baron, February 1997; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
  - EE 350 Peterson #3407, November 6, 1991; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 2)
- Additional papers, Accession ARCH-2012-020